<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Tom Louwerse</title>
    <link>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Tom Louwerse</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; {year} Tom Louwerse</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Who opposes?</title>
      <link>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/project/who-opposes/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/project/who-opposes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    This project is financially supported by the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nwo.nl/en/research-and-results/programmes/nwo/talent-scheme/vidi-awards-2018.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Dutch Research Council (NWO)&lt;/a&gt;. The project starts in December 2019.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main objectives of this project are to measure and explain government-opposition cooperation and to study its consequences for democratic legitimacy and vote choice. Choice is essential to democracy; in modern representative democracies that choice is provided by opposition and governing parties competing in elections. If the choice is to be meaningful, opposition parties have to be distinct from government parties. Previous studies have looked at parties’ distinctiveness in the electoral arena, but what happens in parliament has been overlooked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among scholars as well as the general public, there are increasing concerns regarding the distinctiveness of opposition and government parties in parliament. Scholars have argued that there is a process of opposition blurring in parliament, but the evidence is largely anecdotal and based on single-country studies. This project is the first to provide longitudinal indicators of parliamentary cooperation between government and opposition in four countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The analysis compares established parliamentary democracies with very different political systems: The Netherlands, United Kingdom, Denmark and Canada. Applying innovative content analysis methods to assess parties’ actual parliamentary behaviour and speeches, I will map patterns of parliamentary cooperation between 1945 and 2018. Explanations of those patterns will be based on quantitative data and elite interviews. The effect of government-opposition cooperation on democratic satisfaction, electoral turnout, and vote choice will be studied through analysis of survey material as well as multi-country conjoint survey experiments.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>De PVV in het parlement</title>
      <link>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/publication/2019-otjes-louwerse-wilders-gewogen/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/publication/2019-otjes-louwerse-wilders-gewogen/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;wilders-gewogen.jpg&#34; /&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The political dynamics of portfolio design in European democracies</title>
      <link>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/publication/2019-sieberer-et-al/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/publication/2019-sieberer-et-al/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Note: my contribution to this article was limited to the collection of data on the case of the Netherlands and workshop participation related to this research project.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How Populists Wage Opposition: Parliamentary Opposition Behaviour and Populism in Netherlands</title>
      <link>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/publication/2018-louwerse-otjes/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/publication/2018-louwerse-otjes/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;this-is-an-open-access-publication-i-class-ai-ai-open-access-i-i-class-fab-fa-creative-commons-i&#34;&gt;This is an open access publication &lt;i class=&#34;ai ai-open-access&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;i class=&#34;fab fa-creative-commons&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Inleiding Haagse Tafeltjesavond SIB</title>
      <link>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/talk/2019-04-17-sib/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Apr 2019 19:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/talk/2019-04-17-sib/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Speech at Young Academy Leiden inauguration</title>
      <link>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/talk/2019-03-20-inauguration-yal/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Mar 2019 16:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/talk/2019-03-20-inauguration-yal/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Mijnheer de rector magnificus, mevrouw de vice-rector magnificus, ladies and gentlemen,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a great pleasure to speak to you today on behalf of the first group of members of the Young Academy Leiden in my role as chair. Over the past couple of months, we got the chance to get to know each other: a diverse group of scholars from all of our faculties, with very diverse academic backgrounds, nationally and internationally. Together, we get the unique chance to discover our disciplinary differences and commonalities, and to shape what the Young Academy Leiden is all about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today we will present ourselves, our research and ambitions for the Young Academy Leiden and will also uncover our first major activity a little later in the programme. But first let me reflect on something that has been a key term in university policy and the conception of a Young Academy in Leiden: academic excellence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The term academic excellence has become a buzzword in the academic world. But what does it mean? Sometimes the term excellence is used in an attempt to focus attention and resources on those researchers with unusually good qualities. This ‘super star model’ of science has recently met with criticism, however, from De Jonge Akademie, our big sister organisation at the national level. They argue that the widening gap between the haves and have-nots is not beneficial to a good academic climate. Funding opportunities are, after all, very much limited and many great young scholars with strong proposals cannot be funded. And this in turn leads to unequal chances for further funding and promotion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We too have been selected as members of the Young Academy Leiden in part because of our academic record. But we don’t consider ourselves super stars. We view true academic excellence in different terms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, an excellent university recognises that science is done together. We work together, we build on each other’s arguments. We stand on the shoulders of giants, but also on many normal shoulders of people who have contributed to development in their respective fields.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, an excellent university connects education and research and this requires research active staff across the board. An excellent university allows its students to excel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And thirdly, academic excellence asks us to look beyond our disciplines and to society. Our bastion of liberty should not be an ivory tower, but a sanctuary open to all and connected to the cities of Leiden and The Hague and the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are humbled to get the chance to work on these objectives. To strengthen interdisciplinary exchange, to reach out to society and to reflect on university policy from the perspective of young researchers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We recognize the help over the years of mentors, friends and colleagues. Speaking from my own perspective: sometimes the job of an academic can be very individual, working on your own projects and teaching your own courses. But far more often I receive support from colleagues in many different shapes. From supervisors and mentors, from people critically reflecting upon my work, from discussions at the lunch table about politics and the university. I am sure this is true for all members of the Young Academy Leiden. We are enormously thankful for the help and support given to us and the opportunity provided to be a part of the Young Academy Leiden. Therefore, we very much look forward to working in service of and together with everyone at our university and beyond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is now my great pleasure to present to you the first members of the Young Academy Leiden.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/L6rmxSAkLOE&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>De Stem des Volks</title>
      <link>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/talk/2018-11-16-alumni-event/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Nov 2018 13:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/talk/2018-11-16-alumni-event/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;De Faculteit der Sociale Wetenschappen organiseert deze middag haar 1e alumni event met het thema de uitwisseling tussen wetenschap en praktijk. Waar staat het onderzoek binnen Culturele Antropologie, Pedagogische Wetenschappen en Psychologie nu? Hoe slaan we een brug met het praktische werkveld en onze maatschappelijke omgeving? Hoe kan de wetenschap de ervaringen en innovaties uit de praktijk meenemen? En waar liggen kansen om gezamenlijk op te trekken? Onze wetenschappers vertellen vanuit hun eigen discipline en alumni brengen de ervaringen uit het werkveld.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ik spreek over politieke peilingen en de Peilingwijzer in het bijzonder.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The electoral cycle effect in parliamentary democracies</title>
      <link>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/publication/2018-muller-louwerse-psrm/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/publication/2018-muller-louwerse-psrm/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;this-is-an-open-access-publication-i-class-ai-ai-open-access-i-i-class-fab-fa-creative-commons-i-i-class-fab-fa-creative-commons-by-i&#34;&gt;This is an open access publication &lt;i class=&#34;ai ai-open-access&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;i class=&#34;fab fa-creative-commons&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;i class=&#34;fab fa-creative-commons-by&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Helpen stemhulpen?</title>
      <link>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/talk/2018-10-16-prodemos/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Oct 2018 12:30:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/talk/2018-10-16-prodemos/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;During the first ProDemos &amp;lsquo;knowledge lunch&amp;rsquo; I presented academic research by others and myself on &amp;lsquo;voting advice applications&amp;rsquo;. I talked about their impact and their design, as well as how their design impacts upon the advice they provide.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Nature of Political Representation in Times of Dealignment</title>
      <link>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/project/napre/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/project/napre/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    This project is collaborative work with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.goethe-university-frankfurt.de/50240689/tzittel&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Prof. Dr Thomas Zittel&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.goethe-university-frankfurt.de/82093867/ContentPage_82093867?&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Dr Markus Baumann&lt;/a&gt; (Goethe Universität Frankfurt am Main), &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kcl.ac.uk/people/rosie-campbell&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Prof. Dr Rosie Campbell&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Diane_Bolet&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Diane Bolet&lt;/a&gt; (King&amp;rsquo;s College London) and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.universiteitleiden.nl/medewerkers/wouter-schakel&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Wouter Schakel&lt;/a&gt; (Leiden University). It is financially supported by DFG, ESRC, and NWO under the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nwo.nl/en/news-and-events/news/2018/10/fourteen-dutch-researchers-funded-for-collaborative-projects-across-europe-and-japan.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Open Research Area (ORA)&lt;/a&gt;.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Weakening partisanship in West European electorates results in increasing disconnection between citizens and the state; raising pressing questions regarding future mechanisms of political representation that could sustain responsive government. To explore this serious challenge to democratic governance, this project investigates the viability, and conditions of, dyadic forms of representation in established European democracies. We particularly aim to study whether individual MPs pay attention to citizen-initiated inquiries in low information environments, what types of cues most often gain their attention, and how electoral contexts condition the interactions of citizens and MPs.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data in Representative Democracy</title>
      <link>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/talk/2018-07-03-summerschool/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jul 2018 09:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/talk/2018-07-03-summerschool/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The relationship between politicians and citizens is at the core of representative democracy, but any number of organizations desire some form of representative relationship between themselves and their participants, clients, etc. In the political realm, researchers are using various data sources to study the representative relationship, for example voter studies, elite surveys, text analysis, and data and online tools are increasingly used to strengthen the representative relationship. Voting Advice Applications, for example, use data on party policy positions to present voters with advice on who to vote for. This session will look into the models of what the representative relationship can and should look like, and how data can be used to study and improve this relationship.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Parlementaire oppositie: overal en nergens?</title>
      <link>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/talk/2018-05-18-andeweg/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 May 2018 13:15:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/talk/2018-05-18-andeweg/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Op vrijdag 18 mei 2018 neemt prof. dr. R.B. (Rudy) Andeweg officieel afscheid van de Universiteit Leiden. Voorafgaand aan zijn afscheidsrede organiseert het Instituut Politieke Wetenschap een symposium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Als inleiders/sprekers van dit symposium, onder voorzitterschap van prof. dr. Galen Irwin, zullen optreden:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prof. dr. Kris Deschouwer (Vrije Universiteit Brussel)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prof.dr. Jacques Thomassen (Universiteit Twente)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dr. Tom Louwerse (Universiteit Leiden)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Netherlands: The reinvention of consensus democracy</title>
      <link>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/publication/2018-otjes-louwerse-timmermans/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/publication/2018-otjes-louwerse-timmermans/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Parliamentary Questions as Strategic Party Tools</title>
      <link>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/publication/2017-otjes-louwerse-wep/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/publication/2017-otjes-louwerse-wep/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;this-is-an-open-access-publication-i-class-ai-ai-open-access-i-i-class-fab-fa-creative-commons-i&#34;&gt;This is an open access publication &lt;i class=&#34;ai ai-open-access&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;i class=&#34;fab fa-creative-commons&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Estimating Uncertainty in Party Policy Positions Using the Confrontational Approach</title>
      <link>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/publication/2015-louwerse-pellikaan-psrm/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/publication/2015-louwerse-pellikaan-psrm/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Dutch Parliamentary Behaviour Dataset</title>
      <link>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/publication/2017-louwerse-otjes-vanvonno-actapolitica/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/publication/2017-louwerse-otjes-vanvonno-actapolitica/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Naar nieuwe verhoudingen tussen Kamer en kabinet?</title>
      <link>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/publication/2017-louwerse-van-vonno/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/publication/2017-louwerse-van-vonno/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Beyond rigour: increasing the public relevance of political science and public administration</title>
      <link>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/talk/2017-11-09-vvb/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Nov 2017 10:30:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/talk/2017-11-09-vvb/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Verening voor Bestuurskunde organizes together with the Netherlands Institute of Government an interactive discussion on doing valorisation. Students, PhD students, researchers, professors and wider audience discuss the scientific calling and public relevance of public administration and political science. Panel members include: prof. Sandra van Thiel (Radboud University Nijmegen), dr. Tom Louwerse (Leiden University), prof. Willem Schinkel (Erasmus University of Rotterdam), dr. Sanneke Kuipers (Leiden University), and dr. Thomas Schillemans (Utrecht University).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The panel discussion is led by prof. Mark Bovens (Utrecht University)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reaching across the aisle: Explaining government–opposition voting in parliament</title>
      <link>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/publication/2016-louwerse-etal-party-politics/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/publication/2016-louwerse-etal-party-politics/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Political Representation: Linking Citizens and Representatives </title>
      <link>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/project/political-representation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/project/political-representation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The policy link between voters and politicians has been a central issue in politics for quite some time. My work focuses on the quality of this policy link: are representatives doing what people want?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Polling Aggregation</title>
      <link>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/project/polling-aggregation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/project/polling-aggregation/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Opinion polls are an increasingly central part of election campaigns. My work focuses on the aggregation of opinion polls in Ireland and the Netherlands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;peilingwijzer&#34;&gt;Peilingwijzer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Dutch public broadcaster NOS &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.peilingwijzer.nl&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;publishes&lt;/a&gt; my aggregation of Dutch national opinion polls, called &lt;a href=&#34;http://peilingwijzer.tomlouwerse.nl/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&amp;lsquo;Peilingwijzer&amp;rsquo; (Polling Indicator)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;irish-polling-indicator&#34;&gt;Irish Polling Indicator&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pollingindicator.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Irish Polling Indicator&lt;/a&gt; is published regularly on politicalreform.ie.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Voting Advice Applications</title>
      <link>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/project/vaa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/project/vaa/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Voting Advice Applications have gained a large popular audience over the last decades, but their design has not been studied very elaborately. These tools ask voters for their opinion on a number of salient issues in an election and then present the ‘best match’ between the user’s preferences and the policy preferences of the political parties in a country. In a number of projects, together with different colleagues I have begun to unravel these issues of VAA design. The main question of these studies is: how can we be sure that these tools provide voters with good advice?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Parliaments: rules and behaviour</title>
      <link>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/project/parliaments/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/project/parliaments/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The digital publication of parliamentary data has provided a great incentive for the study of parliamentary behaviour. My current work focuses mainly on the Netherlands, but also Belgium and Sweden as well as country-comparative analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main questions that I focus on are those of patterns of parliamentary (voting) behaviour, particularly with regard to party unity and the government-opposition division in parliament. In addition, I am interested in the concept of (positive and negative) parliamentarism as well as the government formation process.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rol en reikwijdte van de peilingen</title>
      <link>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/talk/2017-05-13-knaw/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 May 2017 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/talk/2017-05-13-knaw/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Waarom zou je peilingen serieus nemen?</title>
      <link>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/talk/2017-04-11-scl/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Apr 2017 20:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/talk/2017-04-11-scl/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Waarom zou je peilingen serieus nemen?</title>
      <link>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/talk/2017-03-30-jal/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Mar 2017 20:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/talk/2017-03-30-jal/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Een verdeeld electoraat?</title>
      <link>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/talk/2017-03-08-ul/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Mar 2017 16:15:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/talk/2017-03-08-ul/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Peilingen: waarom, hoe en waartoe?</title>
      <link>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/talk/2017-01-12-po/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jan 2017 14:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/talk/2017-01-12-po/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Kun je peilingen eigenlijk wel serieus nemen?</title>
      <link>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/talk/2017-uvn/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jan 2017 20:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/talk/2017-uvn/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/xJLcHCfCNw0&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Response Scales in Voting Advice Applications: Do Different Designs Produce Different Outcomes?</title>
      <link>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/publication/2016-rosema-louwerse-pi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/publication/2016-rosema-louwerse-pi/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;this-is-an-open-access-publication-i-class-ai-ai-open-access-i-i-class-fab-fa-creative-commons-i&#34;&gt;This is an open access publication &lt;i class=&#34;ai ai-open-access&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;i class=&#34;fab fa-creative-commons&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Campagne 2017: Kiesgedrag, peilingen &amp; beloftes</title>
      <link>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/talk/2016-10-22-dwars/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/talk/2016-10-22-dwars/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Improving opinion poll reporting: the Irish Polling Indicator</title>
      <link>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/publication/2016-louwerse-ips/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/publication/2016-louwerse-ips/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;this-is-an-open-access-publication-i-class-ai-ai-open-access-i-i-class-fab-fa-creative-commons-i&#34;&gt;This is an open access publication &lt;i class=&#34;ai ai-open-access&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;i class=&#34;fab fa-creative-commons&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Beyond intuition: how sensible use of methodology can improve scientific research</title>
      <link>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/talk/2016-05-12-fft/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 May 2016 12:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/talk/2016-05-12-fft/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Personalised parliamentary behaviour without electoral incentives: the case of the Netherlands</title>
      <link>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/publication/2016-louwerse-otjes-wep/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/publication/2016-louwerse-otjes-wep/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Impact of Parliamentary Specialisation on Cosponsorship</title>
      <link>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/publication/2015-louwerse-otjes-jls/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/publication/2015-louwerse-otjes-jls/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Populists in Parliament: Comparing Left-Wing and Right-Wing Populism in the Netherlands</title>
      <link>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/publication/2015-otjes-louwerse-ps/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/publication/2015-otjes-louwerse-ps/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spatial models in voting advice applications</title>
      <link>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/publication/2014-otjes-louwerse-es/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/publication/2014-otjes-louwerse-es/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Special Majority Cabinet? Supported Minority Governance and Parliamentary Behavior in the Netherlands</title>
      <link>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/publication/2014-otjes-louwerse-wpsr/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/publication/2014-otjes-louwerse-wpsr/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is an English-language version of Otjes &amp;amp; Louwerse (2013) Res Publica 55(4), 459-480&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Een middenkabinet of een minderheidskabinet?</title>
      <link>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/publication/2014-otjes-louwerse-mi/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/publication/2014-otjes-louwerse-mi/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The design effects of voting advice applications: Comparing methods of calculating matches</title>
      <link>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/publication/2014-louwerse-rosema-actapolitica/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/publication/2014-louwerse-rosema-actapolitica/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Parliament without Government: The Belgian Parliament and the Government Formation Processes of 2007–2011</title>
      <link>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/publication/2014-vanaelst-louwerse-wep/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/publication/2014-vanaelst-louwerse-wep/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Keeping promises: VAAs and political representation</title>
      <link>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/publication/2014-fivaz-etal-bc/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/publication/2014-fivaz-etal-bc/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Verkiezingsbeloften: een verouderd ritueel? [Election promises: an obsolete ritual?]</title>
      <link>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/publication/2014-louwerse-rob/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/publication/2014-louwerse-rob/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Een bijzonder meerderheidskabinet? Parlementair gedrag tijdens het kabinet Rutte-I</title>
      <link>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/publication/2013-otjes-louwerse-rp/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/publication/2013-otjes-louwerse-rp/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Politiek in een veranderende wereld: Nederland en België in vergelijkend perspectief.</title>
      <link>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/publication/2013-erk-etal-book/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/publication/2013-erk-etal-book/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This book offers a Dutch-language introduction to comparative politics.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Peilingen in het nieuws: van hypes naar trends</title>
      <link>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/publication/2013-louwerse-benm/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Apr 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/publication/2013-louwerse-benm/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Design challenges in cross-national VAAs: the case of the EU Profiler</title>
      <link>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/publication/2012-louwerse-otjes-ijeg/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Dec 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/publication/2012-louwerse-otjes-ijeg/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Het democratisch mandaat van Nederlandse politieke partijen: crisis of continuïteit?</title>
      <link>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/publication/2012-louwerse-rp/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Dec 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/publication/2012-louwerse-rp/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Leven van Dick Dolman. [Bespreking van: Politiek samenspel: biografische notities]</title>
      <link>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/publication/2012-louwerse-ob/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Dec 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/publication/2012-louwerse-ob/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;leven-van-dick-dolman&#34;&gt;Leven van Dick Dolman&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tien jaar lang was Dick Dolman voorzitter van de Tweede Kamer (1979-1989). In Politiek samenspel kijkt hij terug op zijn privéleven en carrière aan de hand van de mensen die hij daarin ontmoette; in elk hoofdstuk staat één van hen centraal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;De lezer maakt allereerst in staccato kennis met (groot)ouders en familie- en studievrienden. Hoewel dit een aardig inzicht biedt in de ambities van de jonge Dolman, die op jonge leeftijd al op zomerkamp naar de VS gaat en zich later actief in het studentenleven mengt, wordt maar weinig duidelijk over zijn (politieke) keuzes. Waarom een studie economie en actief voor de PvdA? Het lijkt hem te overkomen. Wel is helder dat Dolman al vroeg de basis legde voor een partijpolitieke carrière, want veel van zijn latere PvdA-collega’s leert hij in deze periode al kennen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;De terugblik op zijn periode als Kamervoorzitter richt zich veelal op zijn representatieve taken. Over het werk in de Kamer valt maar weinig te lezen, met uitzondering van enkele van elders overgenomen toespraken en bijdragen. Zo wordt aan zijn eigen verkiezing als Kamervoorzitter slechts een enkele alinea besteed, terwijl het interessant zou zijn om te lezen hoe de gang van zaken destijds afwijkt van de open procedure waarin voorzitters sinds 2002 worden verkozen. Een inkijkje in de dagelijkse werkzaamheden van de voorzitter wordt geboden wanneer Dolman beschrijft dat hij soms alle fracties liet nabellen als nog niet de nodige 76 leden de presentielijst hadden getekend of als hij de uitbreiding van de personele ondersteuning van Kamerleden en de verbouwing van het Kamergebouw optekent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Politiek samenspel is vooral een commentaar op gebeurtenissen in Dolmans carrière. Het biedt de lezer weinig context, waardoor het soms lastig te volgen zal zijn voor iemand die niet (meer) zo goed bekend is met de parlementaire geschiedenis van de jaren ’70 en ’80. Zelf vermeldt Dolman dat hij lang geen memoires wilde schrijven omdat hij in de politiek ‘geen echt belangrijke dingen’ zou hebben gedaan. Daarmee onderschat hij wellicht onbedoeld zijn rol als Kamervoorzitter. Dit boek smaakt naar meer, juist daarover.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Feitenvrije vs meningenvrije politiek</title>
      <link>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/publication/2012-louwerse-idee/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Oct 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/publication/2012-louwerse-idee/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mechanisms of Issue Congruence: The Democratic Party Mandate</title>
      <link>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/publication/2012-louwerse-wep/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Oct 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/publication/2012-louwerse-wep/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Loyaal met een scherpe rand</title>
      <link>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/publication/2011-louwerse-otjes-ul/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/publication/2011-louwerse-otjes-ul/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Political parties and the democratic mandate. Comparing Collective mandate fulfilment in the United Kingdom and the Netherlands.</title>
      <link>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/publication/2011-louwerse-thesis/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jun 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/publication/2011-louwerse-thesis/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Spatial Approach to the Party Mandate</title>
      <link>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/publication/2011-louwerse-pa/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Mar 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/publication/2011-louwerse-pa/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Kies voor de liberale democratie</title>
      <link>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/publication/2010-otjes-louwerse-helling/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Sep 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/publication/2010-otjes-louwerse-helling/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mapping Policy Preferences II: Estimates for Parties, Electors, and Governments in Eastern Europe, European Union and OECD 1990-2003 [Book review]</title>
      <link>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/publication/2009-louwerse-actapolitica/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/publication/2009-louwerse-actapolitica/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
