<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects on Tom Louwerse</title>
    <link>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/project/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Projects on Tom Louwerse</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018 Tom Louwerse</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 10 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/project/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Parliaments: rules and behaviour</title>
      <link>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/project/parliaments/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/project/parliaments/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;The digital publication of parliamentary data has provided a great incentive for the study of parliamentary behaviour. My current work focuses mainly on the Netherlands, but also Belgium and Sweden as well as country-comparative analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main questions that I focus on are those of patterns of parliamentary (voting) behaviour, particularly with regard to party unity and the government-opposition division in parliament. In addition, I am interested in the concept of (positive and negative) parliamentarism as well as the government formation process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;current-working-and-conference-papers&#34;&gt;Current (working and conference) papers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Louwerse, T. (2017) The Blurring of Opposition: Measuring Government-Opposition Relations in Parliament. Paper presented at the General Conference of the European Political Science Association, Milan, 22-24 June, and at the 4th Conference of the ECPR Standing Group on Parliaments, Basel, 29 June-1 July 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Otjes, S., Louwerse, T. &amp;amp; Timmermans, A.  (2017) Populism and Opposition Party Behaviour in Netherlands. Paper presented at he 4th Conference of the ECPR Standing Group on Parliaments, Basel, 29 June-1 July 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Otjes, S., Louwerse, T. &amp;amp; Timmermans A. (2016) &lt;a href=&#34;https://ecpr.eu/Events/PaperDetails.aspx?PaperID=28743&amp;amp;EventID=95&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;The Reinvention of Consensus Democracy: Opposition Party Behaviour in the Netherlands, 1998-2015&lt;/a&gt;. Paper presented at the ECPR General Conference, Prague, 7-10 September.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Louwerse, T. (2015) The concept of &amp;lsquo;positive&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;negative&amp;rsquo; parliamentarism. Paper presented at the workshop &amp;lsquo;Vague concepts and poor operationalization – solutions to measurement problems in studies of government formation&amp;rsquo;, Stockholm, 16-18 September.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Political Representation: Linking Citizens and Representatives </title>
      <link>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/project/political-representation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/project/political-representation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The policy link between voters and politicians has been a central issue in politics for quite some time. My work focuses on the quality of this policy link: are representatives doing what people want?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Polling Aggregation</title>
      <link>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/project/polling-aggregation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/project/polling-aggregation/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Opinion polls are an increasingly central part of election campaigns. My work focuses on the aggregation of opinion polls in Ireland and the Netherlands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;peilingwijzer&#34;&gt;Peilingwijzer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Dutch public broadcaster NOS &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.peilingwijzer.nl&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;publishes&lt;/a&gt; my aggregation of Dutch national opinion polls, called &lt;a href=&#34;http://peilingwijzer.tomlouwerse.nl/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&amp;lsquo;Peilingwijzer&amp;rsquo; (Polling Indicator)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;irish-polling-indicator&#34;&gt;Irish Polling Indicator&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pollingindicator.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Irish Polling Indicator&lt;/a&gt; is published regularly on politicalreform.ie.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Voting Advice Applications</title>
      <link>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/project/vaa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.tomlouwerse.nl/project/vaa/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Voting Advice Applications have gained a large popular audience over the last decades, but their design has not been studied very elaborately. These tools ask voters for their opinion on a number of salient issues in an election and then present the ‘best match’ between the user’s preferences and the policy preferences of the political parties in a country. In a number of projects, together with different colleagues I have begun to unravel these issues of VAA design. The main question of these studies is: how can we be sure that these tools provide voters with good advice?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
